Guide to the Philip Turner Papers, 1751-1858, 1881 and undated RL.01315
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Philip Turner papers
1751-1858, 1881 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Turner, Philip, 1740-1815
RL.01315
6 Linear Feet
Philip Turner (1740-1815) was a noted surgeon from Norwich, Connecticut and New York, New York. The Philip Turner Papers Collection spans from 1751 to 1858 and contains correspondence, military hospital returns, printed material, a logbook, and ledgers documenting Philip Turner's career as a surgeon in private practice in Norwich, Connecticut and New York, New York, in the Continental Army, and in the United States Army. Items include correspondence with George Washington, Thomas Jefferson, William Eustis, Henry Dearborn, John Morgan, William Shippen, and other prominent Americans. Also includes materials on Turner's family. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Philip Turner Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2011 and 2018.
Historical Note
Philip Turner (1740-1815) was a noted surgeon from Norwich, Connecticut, where he trained under his foster father, Dr. Elisha Tracy. He served with the Continental Army during the Revolutionary War, holding the position of Surgeon General of the Eastern Department. After the Revolutionary War, Turner returned to private practice in Norwich, and moved to New York in 1800. He also served as an army surgeon during the French and Indian War (1754-1763) and the War of 1812, when he was stationed at Fort Columbus on Governor's Island, New York. Turner died in 1815.
Philip and Lucy Turner had seven children, two of whom appear as authors of material in the collection. John Turner (1764-1837) was also a doctor in Norwich, Connecticut. Nancy Turner married Marvin Wait in 1810, and had a son, John Turner Wait (1811-1899), who served as a U.S. Representative from Connecticut and also authored material in the collection.
Chronology List
Feb. 25, 1740 Philip Turner born in Norwich, Connecticut to Captain Philip Turner and Anne Huntington Adgate.
1758 Turner began his military service as a surgeon during the French and Indian War (1754-1763).
April 7, 1763 Turner married Lucy Tracy, daughter of Dr. Elisha Tracy.
1775-1783 Revolutionary War
June 17, 1775 Battle of Bunker Hill. Turner was present as a military surgeon.
July 6, 1775 Turner was commissioned surgeon to the 8th Regiment Connecticut troops.
Dec. 16, 1775 Turner was discharged from the army.
April 1777 Turner received the appointment of Surgeon General of the Hospital, Eastern Department.
1781 Turner retired from military service and returned to Norwich, Connecticut to open a private practice.
1800 Turner moved to New York, New York.
1802 Turner re-entered military service as a surgeon's mate.
Nov. 1809 Turner was transferred to Fort Columbus on Governor's Island.
1812-1815 War of 1812
April 20, 1815 Turner died at the age of seventy-five.
Collection Overview
The Philip Turner Papers Collection spans from 1751 to 1858 and contains correspondence, military hospital returns, printed material, a logbook, and ledgers documenting Philip Turner's career as a surgeon in private practice in Norwich, Connecticut and New York, New York, in the Continental Army, and in the United States Army. Turner served in the Revolutionary War and the War of 1812, during which he was stationed at Fort Columbus, New York. Included are an extensive collection of military hospital returns from the Eastern Department of the Continental Army describing the state of the Army's sick and wounded and spanning the years 1777 to 1780. Also included is correspondence with George Washington, Tench Coxe, and William Eustis about the procurement of medical supplies and the organization of the Army's medical department during the Revolutionary War and the War of 1812. After the Revolutionary War, Turner felt that he had not received due compensation for his service, and the collection contains extensive correspondence relating to the decades-long effort of Turner and his heirs to receive this compensation from Congress. This correspondence includes letters to and from Thomas Jefferson, Henry Dearborn, John Morgan, William Shippen, and other prominent Americans. Additional correspondence, especially with Daniel Parker, Chief Clerk of the War Department, documents Turner's efforts to secure a commission during the War of 1812.
Also included in the collection are correspondence, financial and legal papers, and poetry relating to Turner's family. The majority of this series is addressed to or stems from John Turner and Nancy Turner, two of Philip Turner's children. Correspondents represented include Judith Sargent Murray, American essayist and advocate for women's rights, and her husband, John Murray. Some of the material is related to the efforts of John Turner and John Turner Wait (Philip Turner's grandson) to receive compensation for Turner's Revolutionary War service. The collection also includes a small hide-covered trunk bearing the initials A.T., possibly belonging to Turner's mother Ann.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged in eight series: Artifacts; Correspondence; Financial and Legal Papers; Journals; Peace Service in New York; Revolutionary War; Turner Family Papers; and War of 1812.
Physicians -- United States -- Correspondence; Military pensions; Military hospitals -- United States; Medicine, Military; Fort Columbus (N.Y.); United States -- History -- War of 1812 -- Medical care; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Medical care; Surgeons -- United States -- Correspondence; Diaries; Ledgers (account books); New York (N.Y.); Norwich, Connecticut; Broadsides (notices); Turner family; Turner, John, 1764-1837; Stoddard, Amos, 1762-1813; Tucker, Thomas Tudor, 1745-1828; Shippen, William, 1712-1801; Simmons, William; Parker, Daniel; Sherman, Roger, 1721-1793; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Wait, John Turner, 1811-1899; United States. Army; United States. Continental Army. Eastern Dept; Turner, Philip, 1740-1815; Armstrong, John, 1758-1843; Coxe, Tench, 1755-1824; Dearborn, Henry, 1751-1829; Eustis, William, 1753-1825; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Morgan, John, 1735-1789; Murray, Judith Sargent, 1751-1820
- Artifact, probably 18th c., 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Small hide-covered trunk decorated with round nailheads that form the initials A.T. The trunk could have belonged to Turner's mother, whose maiden name was Anne Huntington Adgate.
  - Trunk, probably 18th c. (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1780-1813, 3 folders
  Contains personal and professional correspondence chiefly relating to Turner's private practice. Topics include a trip Turner took to Charleston, South Carolina in 1792, requests for Turner's medical services and advice, and two letters asking Turner to cover a debt owed to his son-in-law. Significant correspondents are many, including Revolutionary War period military officials and physicians; there is also an exchange of two letters between Turner and George Washington on the topic of Turner's plan to reorganize the medical department of the Continental Army (the plan is not included), and eight letters from Turner to Thomas Jefferson (1805-1807) regarding Turner's claim for proper compensation for his military service and Turner's views of Jefferson's political situation. Also included is a letter from Judith Sargent Murray to Turner's wife, Lucy, concerning Turner's daughter Elizabeth's visit to Sargent Murray. Many other pieces of correspondence are also located in the Peace Service in New York, Revolutionary War, Turner Family Papers, and War of 1812 Series. Arranged in chronological order.
  - General Correspondence, 1789-1813 (1 folder)
    - Letter, Nov., 1789, from Hannah Abell, Norwich, Conn., to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 30 Nov., 1790, from Judith Sargent Murray, Gloucester, Mass., to Lucy Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 7 Sept., 1792, from Philip Turner, Norwich, Conn., to Dr. David Olyphant, Newport (Box 2)
    - Letter, 12 Sept., 1792, from Philip Turner, Norwich, Conn., to Dr. David Olyphant (Box 2)
    - Memorandum, 18 Sept., 1792, from Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Certificate, 3 Nov., 1800, from Robert Benson, New York (Box 2)
    - Letter, 24 July, 1803, from Malachi Foot, Benjamin Prince, Daniel D. Walters, and Philip D. Keteltas, New York, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 5 Aug., 1803, from Edward Livingston to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 14 Nov., 1803, from unknown to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 14 Nov., 1803, from W. Leffingwell, New Haven, to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
    - Letter, 7 Jan., 1804, from John Franks to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
    - Letter, 19 Jan., 1804, from Colonel Graham to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 11 Feb., 1804, from John Franks, Southhold, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 16 Jan., 1805, from Perez Jones, New York, to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
    - Letter, 4 Feb., 1806, from Cornelius Cooper, New York, to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
    - Letter, 31 Mar., 1806, from Dr. Sage, Sag Harbor, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 28 Aug., 1808, from Clarissa Turner, Lancaster, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 20 Nov., 1808, from Mr. Weston, New York, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 17 Mar., 1809, from J.E.A. Masters, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 17 Mar., 1809, from Charles Carew, New London, to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
    - Letter, 8 May, 1809, from R. Chandernette, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 12 May, 1809, from Commanding Officer, Ellis Island, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 15 Feb., 1810, from S. Williams, New York, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 28 May, 1812, from Philip Turner, New York, to Joel Austin Wallingford (Box 2)
    - Letter, 12 Sept., 1812, from W. Sheldon, New York, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 29 Mar., 1813, from J. Thomas, Worcester, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Memorandum, 1813, The Case of Mrs. Vanderventer and the Cause of her Death, from Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - George Washington, 1780 (1 folder)
    - Letter, 3 Feb., 1780, from Philip Turner, Danbury, to George Washington, Morristown (Box 2)
    - Letter, 24 Feb., 1780, from George Washington, Morristown, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Thomas Jefferson, 1805-1807 (1 folder)
    - Letter, 10 Oct., 1805, from Philip Turner, New York, to Thomas Jefferson (Box 2)
    - Letter, 18 Oct., 1805, from Thomas Jefferson, Washington, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 18 Nov., 1805, from Philip Turner, New York, to Thomas Jefferson (Box 2)
    - Letter, 28 Dec., 1805, from Philip Turner, New York, to Thomas Jefferson (Box 2)
    - Letter, 28 Jan., 1806, from Philip Turner, New York, to Thomas Jefferson (Box 2)
    - Letter, 28 Feb., 1806, from Philip Turner, to Thomas Jefferson (Box 2)
    - Letter, 16 June, 1806, from Philip Turner, New York, to Thomas Jefferson (Box 2)
    - Letter, 21 July, 1807, from Philip Turner, to Thomas Jefferson (Box 2)
- Financial and Legal Papers Series, 1751-1815 and undated, 2 folders and 2 boxes
  Drafts and receipts made out to Philip Turner, the majority for his medical care in Norwich, Connecticut and New York, New York. Also included are a draft made out to Capt. Philip Turner (Turner's father) by Benedict Arnold Sr. (father of the notable son of the same name), the Norwich land deed made out to Turner's father, an account ledger for John Morgan kept during the Revolutionary War, and two financial ledgers documenting Turner's private practice.
  - Drafts, deeds, and receipts, 1751-1810 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Ledgers, 1784-1815 and undated (1 folder, 2 boxes)
    - Ledgers, undated (Box 2)
    - Financial ledger: private practice, 1784-1801 (Box 6)
    - Financial ledger: private practice, 1811-1815 (Box 7)
- Journals Series, 1774-1803, 1 box
  Two volumes: "Philip Turner's Day-Book, March 19, 1803" and "Philip Turner's Medical Collections and Experimental Observations" (circa 1774-1801). Originally used to record information on Turner's patients, more than half the pages in the daybook have been pasted over with later newspaper clippings (circa 1830s), presumably by Turner's grandson, John Turner Wait, whose name appears on the inside cover of the volume.
  - "Philip Turner's Medical Collections and Experimental Observations" (circa 1774-1801) (Box 7)
- Peace Service in New York Series, 1809-1811 and undated, 1 folder
  Chiefly correspondence relating to Turner's assignment as surgeon's mate at Fort Columbus on Governor's Island, New York. Correspondents include William Eustis (then Secretary of War), Henry Dearborn, Thomas Tudor Tucker (Treasurer of the United States), William Simmons (accountant of the War Department), and Tench Coxe (purveyor of public supplies). The majority of the correspondence deals with the ordering and delivery of medical supplies for Fort Columbus, in particular the absence of supplies and complaints about the problems associated with their delivery. Also included are correspondence and several documents detailing Turner's pay for his service.
  - Letter, 7 Feb., 1809, from Henry Dearborn, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Ms.,Subsistence Account of Philip Turner, post surgeon's Mate at Ellis's and Bedlows Islands in New York Bay, Apr. 7, 1809 (Box 2)
  - Letter, 27 Apr., 1809, from William Eustis, Washington, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Ms., P. Turner's Account for medical services, subsistence and storage from the 7th of Feb. to the 7th of May 1809 (Box 2)
  - Letter, 6 June, 1809, from William Eustis, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Letter, 6 July, 1809, from William Simmons, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Letter, 8 July, 1809, from Tench Coxe, Philadelphia, to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
  - Letter, 16 July, 1809, from Philip Turner, New York, to Callender Irvine (Box 2)
  - Letter, 19 July, 1809, from Callender Irvine, Philadelphia, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Letter, 9 Sept., 1809, from Charles Gardner, Fort Columbus, to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
  - Letter, 28 Sept., 1809, from William Eustis, Boston, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Letter, 30 Sept., 1809, from William Simmons, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Ms., P. Turner's Account from the 1st of July to the 30th of Sept., 1809 (Box 2)
  - Letter, 4 Nov., 1809, from Philip Turner, New York, to William Eustis (Box 2)
  - Letter, 20 Dec., 1809, from William Eustis, to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
  - Letter, 2 Jan., 1810, from William Simmons, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Letter, 17 Feb., 1810, from Philip Turner, New York, to William Eustis (Box 2)
  - Letter, 7 May, 1810, from Philip Turner, New York, to Tench Coxe (Box 2)
  - Letter, 18 May, 1810, from Philip Turner, New York, to Richard Reece, London, England (Box 2)
  - Letter, 19 May, 1810, from Tench Coxe, to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
  - Letter, 28 May, 1810, from Callender Irvine, to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
  - Letter, 3 Oct., 1810, from Thomas Tudor Tucker, Washington, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Letter, 12 Nov., 1810, from William Eustis, to Philip Turner, New York (Box 2)
  - Letter, 29 Nov., 1810, from William Simmons, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
  - Letter, Nov., 1810, from Philip Turner, New York, to William Simmons (Box 2)
  - Letter, 3 June, 1811, from Philip Turner, Fort Columbus, New York, to Tench Coxe, Philadelphia (Box 2)
  - Letter, 6 June, 1811, from Tench Coxe, Philadelphia, to Philip Turner, Fort Columbus, New York (Box 2)
  - Letter, 10 June, 1811, from Philip Turner, Fort Columbus, New York, to Tench Coxe, Philadelphia (Box 2)
  - Letter, 11 June, 1811, from Tench Coxe, Philadelphia, to Philip Turner, Fort Columbus, New York (Box 2)
  - Letter, 26 July, 1811, from Philip Turner, New York, to William Simmons (Box 2)
  - Letter, 29 Sept., 1811, from Philip Turner, New York, to William Eustis (Box 2)
  - Letter, 29 Sept., 1811, from Philip Turner, New York, to William Simmons (Box 2)
  - Letter, 12 Oct., 1811, from Philip Turner, Fort Columbus, to William Simmons (Box 2)
  - Letter, undated, from Philip Turner, to Tench Coxe (Box 2)
- Revolutionary War Series, 1776-1858 and undated, 13 folders
  Arranged into four subseries documenting Philip Turner's service as a surgeon during the Revolutionary War. The Correspondence Subseries includes letters to and from John Morgan, William Shippen, Roger Sherman, and Samuel Huntington. Topics in the correspondence include Turner's military orders from John Morgan, as well as orders issued by Turner and others, regulations from William Eustis for the military hospital in Danbury, Connecticut, and discussions about the procurement of supplies.
  The Military Hospital Returns Subseries documents the medical state of the Continental Army's sick and wounded in the Eastern Department (including New Hampshire, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, and Connecticut) during the Revolutionary War. The subseries consists of weekly reports sent to Turner from military hospitals in towns in the Eastern Department listing the number of patients admitted and discharged, and the number of patients with a variety of illnesses, including dysentery, fever, and rheumatism, as well as those wounded in battle. These hospital return forms are for the most part standardized and handwritten, with several using printed forms.
  The Printed Materials Subseries contains Congressional resolutions concerning the establishment and running of military hospitals.
  The Revolutionary War Claims Subseries contains correspondence relating to the efforts of Turner and his heirs from 1779 to 1858 to receive from Congress what Turner considered proper compensation for his military service. The discrepancies resulted from a disagreement as to Turner's exact rank and to the resulting difference in pay. In an effort to receive compensation, Turner wrote numerous letters to Secretary of War Henry Dearborn, and corresponded with a number of prominent individuals, including General Huntington, William Eustis, and Joseph B. Varnum. Turner also submitted petitions to Congress and to the Connecticut General Assembly. Other correspondence with Thomas Jefferson relating to Turner's Revolutionary War claims can be found in the Correspondence Series.
  - Correspondence, 1776-1781 and undated (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Letter, 4 Nov., 1776, from John Morgan, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 10 Nov., 1776, from John Morgan, camp near White Plains, to unknown (Box 2)
    - Letter, Nov., 1776, from John Morgan, to the Regimental Surgeons (Box 2)
    - Letter, 9 May, 1777, from John Morgan, Boston, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 18 Apr., 1778, from John Morgan, New Haven, to Philip Turner, Danbury (Box 2)
    - Letter, 30 Apr., 1778, from Philip Turner, to Isaac Foster (Box 2)
    - Letter, 17 Apr., 1778, from Edwin Bulkley, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 18 Aug., 1778, from Edwin Bulkley, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 17 Sept., 1778, from Philip Turner, Danbury, to Lieutenant Mack (Box 2)
    - Letter, 16 Nov., 1778, from Philip Turner, Danbury, to Doctor Hosmer (Box 2)
    - Letter, 19 Dec., 1778, Some regulations necessary to be adopted with respect to the General Hospital in Danbury in order to make the patients comfortable and to do them that justice to which they are entitled and which Congress expects they receive, from William Eustis, Danbury, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 16 Mar., 1779, from Philip Turner, Danbury, to William Shippen (Box 2)
    - Letter, 20 Apr., 1779, from William Shippen, Somerset, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 1 June, 1779, from Thomas Fanning, Norwich, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 9 June, 1779, from Abiel Hyde, Norwich, to John Baryan, Danbury (Box 2)
    - Letter, 4 July, 1779, from Philip Turner, Danbury, to unknown (Box 2)
    - Letter, 4 Aug., 1779, from John Tyler, New London, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 19 Aug., 1779, from John Tyler, New London, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 4 Sept., 1779, from John Tyler, New London, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 2 Nov., 1779, from Roger Sherman, Philadelphia, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 1779, from Philip Turner, to William Eustis (Box 2)
    - Letter, 4 Feb., 1780, from Philip Turner, Danbury, to Samuel Huntington (Box 2)
    - Letter, 8 Feb., 1780, from Roger Sherman, Philadelphia, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 16 Apr., 1780, from Philip Turner, Providence, to Doctor Adams (Box 2)
    - Ms., Resolve of Congress, May 1780 (Box 2)
    - Letter, 21 June, 1780, from George Bright, New London, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 5 Aug., 1780, from John De La Mater, Boston, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 2 Sept., 1780, from Roger Sherman, Philadelphia, to Philip Turner, Danbury (Box 2)
    - Letter, 24 Nov., 1780, Account sent to Congress from Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 19 Dec., 1780, from William Ledyard, New London, to Philip Turner, Norwich (Box 2)
    - Letter, 15 Jan., 1781, from William Ledyard, New London, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 28 June, 1781, from John De La Mater, Danbury, to Philip Turner (Box 2)
    - Letter, 30 June, 1781, from John Cochran, New London, to Philip Turner, Norwich (Box 2)
    - Letter, 1781, from Philip Turner, to Roger Sherman (Box 2)
    - Letter, undated, from Philip Turner, to John Trumbull (Box 2)
    - Letter, undated, from Philip Turner, to Harry Burton (Box 2)
    - Letter, undated, from Philip Turner, On Dr. Tilton's errand to the Army, to unknown (Box 2)
    - Letter, undated, from Philip Turner, Directions for Doctor Shippen (Box 2)
    - Letter, undated, from Philip Turner, to Mr. Thompson, Hartford (Box 2)
    - Letter, undated, from Philip Turner, to William Shippen (Box 2)
    - Letter, undated, from Philip Turner, to Doctors Adams and Custin (Box 2)
    - Ms., Account of the Money Paid for the use of the Hospital in North [illegible], Paid by Colonel Prentice, undated (Box 2)
    - Letter, undated, from Philip Turner, to the Senior Officer of the Military Hospital at Providence (Box 2)
    - Letter, undated, from Philip Turner, to the Senior Officer of the Military Hospitals, Eastern District (Box 2)
  - Military Hospital Returns, 1777-1780 and undated (5 folders)
    - Military Hospital Returns, 1777 (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Military Hospital Returns, 1778 (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Oversize Military Hospital Returns, 1778 (1 folder) (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Military Hospital Returns, 1779 (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Miltiary Hospital Returns, 1780 and undated (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Printed Material, 1777-1780 (1 folder)
    - In Congress Resolved..., April 7, 1777 (Box 4)
    - Philip Turner, Rules and Directions for the Better Regulating the Military Hospital of the United States, Feb. 6, 1778 (Box 4)
    - Plan for Conducting the Hospital Department of the United States, Sept. 30, 1780 (Box 4)
  - Revolutionary War Claims, 1779-1858 and undated (5 folders) (Box 5)
    Arranged in original order, possibly in groups originally bundled together.
- Turner Family Papers Series, 1776-1840, 1881 and undated, 3 folders